A Guide to the Contents of the Original Letters Collection 1761-1916
Roanoke Public Libraries
Roanoke Public Libraries
A Guide to the Original Letters Collection
Roanoke Public Libraries
1963.1.15
1 drop-front storage box
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Mrs. J.W. Gaut
Historical Note
The collection contains various correspondences from numerous authors at different dates. The letters that pertain to Roanoke are those of John Randolph, who resided here in the 1800s. The majority of letters date from the late 1820s and are written to Randolph’s cousin, Maria. The remaining letters range in date and cover a variety of topics. The oldest correspondence comes from the shipping company of Champe, Ward and Hunter to John Backhouse, an English shipping magnate, regarding debts owed. A large portion of the letters appear to be legal in nature, discussing court dates and suits filed. The last folders in the collection contain land deeds for property in Roanoke County.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 1 drop-front storage box containing 18 folders. In addition to loose correspondence, a scrapbook of 10 letters and a deeds for Roanoke County properties are included. Description for this small collection is at item level.
Arrangement
Documents are arranged by document type.
Contents List
- Original Letters Collection (Box 1)
  - Acknowledgement letter from George Garretson to Mrs. J.W. Gaut 15 January 1963 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Robert Lee to Robert Standard, Esq. July 1916 (Folder 2)
  - Letter from James Monroe to an unknown recipient 19 December 1813 (Folder 3)
  - Letter from Benjamin Harrison to Robert Standard, Esq. 5 December 1817 (Folder 4)
  - Letter from an unknown author to William Wirt, Esq. 13 August 1817 (Folder 5)
  - Letters included in scrapbook as follows: 1) R. E. Lee to J.S. Wolfe, 2) To unknown recipient from unknown author, 3) James Hunter of Champe, Ward and Hunter to John Blackhouse, 4) Unknown author to Tom Dean, 5) Largely illegible due to condition, 6) Unknown author to Adam Craig, 7) Champe, Ward and Hunter to John Blackhouse, 8) Unknown author to Robert Standard, 9) Unknown author to Adam Craig, 10) G.W. Hay to Robert Standard 12 September 1761-24 January 1914 (Folder 6)
  - An inventory of the letters in collection from John Randolph unknown date (Folder 7)
  - Seal of Remembrance from Maria Ward to John Randolph undated (Folder 8)
  - Information on the Seal of Remembrance from Folder 8 by an unknown author undated (Folder 9)
  - Letter from John Randolph to James Bouldin regarding land 16 December 1816 (Folder 10)
  - Letter from John Randolph to John Reynolds regarding list of books to be sent to Reynolds at the closing of Congress 19 March 1809 (Folder 11)
  - Ten letters from John Randolph to his cousin, Maria Coleman 8 December 1827-3 July 1829 (Folder 12)
  - Biographical note on John Randolph undated (Folder 13)
  - Letter from John Randolph to Howson Clark 31 July, year unknown (Folder 14)
  - Four letters from John Randolph to Howson Clark 13 January 1822-17 February 1823 (Folder 15)
  - Five letters from Emma Berger to various recipients 29 March 1870-30 January 1889 (Folder 16)
  - Roanoke County Deeds and Surveys for Lewis Huff and Fanny Petty 18 February 1867 (Folder 17)
  - Roanoke County Deeds and Surveys: 1) R.J. Jordan and Ann Dickenson, 2) Ann Dickenson and Jessee Oliver, 3) Survey notes from James E. Day 13 September 1890-10 January 1891 (Folder 18)